<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Bartosz Jabłoński - IT Blog and Travel Blog</title>
        <link>https://bartas93.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>Bartosz Jabłoński - IT Blog and Travel Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 09:30:37 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello, world.]]></title>
            <link>https://bartas93.github.io/blog/hello-world</link>
            <guid>hello-world</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 09:30:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[When it comes to social media, I'm definitely more a reader than a writer type of person. Recently I've felt a need to start creating content. Or, more like get back into doing it.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to social media, I'm definitely more a reader than a writer type of person. Recently I've felt a need to start creating content. Or, more like get back into doing it.</p><p>The last time I had a blog was more than 15 years ago. As a teenager, I used to run the "My IT News" WordPress site with, as you may expect, news around IT - especially the new consumer electronics products. While it didn't have much attention (as far as I remember, around ~5k unique visitors per month), I enjoyed doing it. But I had plenty of time and energy back then. Today I'm struggling with both, so... I'm starting a new blog! That makes sense, right?</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_rv3c" id="why-yet-another-blog">Why yet another blog<a class="hash-link" href="#why-yet-another-blog" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Nowadays, everyone has their own blog. Do I really need to become another wannabe influencer?</p><p>No. What I want to achieve is:</p><ul><li>structure my knowledge and record what I've learned recently,</li><li>try out new ways to increase productivity, stay motivated and avoid burnout,</li><li>improve my English (as a non-native English speaker),</li><li>develop self-discipline, reduce procrastination, and, as a result, save time to do the things mentioned above.</li></ul><p>So, as you can see, it's mostly for me, but I hope you'll benefit from this as well.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_rv3c" id="what-to-expect">What to expect<a class="hash-link" href="#what-to-expect" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Well, definitely shorter, more concise blog posts, like this one.</p><p>While I have a few ideas for new blog posts in mind, I don't want to limit myself to just technical topics. Instead, I will probably touch on different areas of my interest, such as:</p><ul><li>full-stack technical topics related to the technologies I use (Go, Kubernetes, React.js, JavaScript, TypeScript, GraphQL, gRPC...),</li><li>personal projects announcements,</li><li>new talks announcements</li><li>open source,</li><li>cool projects and apps I stumbled upon,</li><li>productivity,</li><li>personal growth (i.e. soft skills),</li><li>finance.</li></ul><p>Yup, that's a lot - but we'll see how it goes.</p><p>At some point, I would also like to experiment with the form of the content. Videos, podcasts? Maybe one day...</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_rv3c" id="closing-words">Closing words<a class="hash-link" href="#closing-words" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Please note that my previous blog posts published on different platforms won't be moved. There are just very few of them, though. To read them, see my profiles on <a href="https://medium.com/@pkosiec" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Medium</a> and <a href="https://dev.to/pkosiec" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dev.to</a>.</p><p>If you got to this point, then congratulations. Welcome to my blog 👋</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>shorts</category>
            <category>hello</category>
            <category>world</category>
            <category>introduction</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Calculating TODO]]></title>
            <link>https://bartas93.github.io/blog/calculating-string-footprint</link>
            <guid>calculating-string-footprint</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Short:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_rv3c" id="short">Short:<a class="hash-link" href="#short" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><ul><li>Na pamięć obiektu String składa się 24 byte na metadane + ilość znaków razy 1 byte lub 2 byte w zależności od wartości coder<ul><li>Metadane : mark word x2 (4 bytes x2 = 8 bytes), klass word (4 bytes), referencja do tablicy byte[] lub char[] (4 byte), hash (4 byte), hashIsZero (1 byte), coder (1 byte),  padding (2 byte)</li></ul></li><li>Obiekt String ma dodatkowW Stringu poza podstawowymi flagami w pamięci (mark word 4 bytes x2, klass word), referencją</li><li>gdy <code>coder =1</code> to kodowanie UTF-16 (2 bytes na znak)</li><li>gdy <code>coder = 0</code> to kodowanie LATIN-1 (1 byte na znak)</li><li>hashIsZero jest to flaga która mówi czy obliczenie hasha zostało już wykonane</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_rv3c" id="jol---string">JOL - String<a class="hash-link" href="#jol---string" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Od Java 9 używamy Compact String czyli jeśli to możliwe to używamy kodowania LATIN-1 a jak nie to ustawiany jest coder=1 i używamy UTF-16. </p><p>(Przed Java 9 wszystko sprowadzało się do char[] i każda literka była równa 2 byte Utf-16.) </p><p>Jeśli chociaż jeden znak będzie inny niż latin-1 (1 byte) to każdy znak w Stringu jest kodowany w utf16 (2 byte).</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>jvm</category>
            <category>jol</category>
            <category>footprint</category>
            <category>string</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>